May 7th
After spending the rest of Golden Week studying
with Oga Kazuomi and Onoya An (Support Division),
Kaizaki Arata passed his fourth round of make-up tests.
These make-ups are from a school far better
than his actual ability, so this is impressive.
As I've written above,
ReLIFE is fraught with trouble.
（夜明(よあけ)）以上のように—
リライフを行ううえで
トラブルはつきものだが—
But each time Kaizaki Arata
demonstrates remorse,
海崎(かいざき)新太(あらた)においては 毎回
反省と改善の態度も見られ…
and attempts to improve...
As I've written above, ReLIFE is fraught with trouble.
But each time Kaizaki Arata demonstrates remorse,
and attempts to improve...
（リライフ社員）
よくないうわさを聞いたよ
We've heard some disturbing rumors.
Specifically, that you're getting
unnecessarily close to the subjects.
君が必要以上に被験者との
接触を図ろうとしている と
（リライフ社員）
サポート課としての立場を—
Have you forgotten you are only Support?
忘れているんじゃないのか？
（リライフ社員）
初めてのことで—
I know it's your first,
and you want to rush things.
焦る気持ちも
分からんではないが—
だからといって—
But that's no excuse for driving the subject
into a corner with unwarranted advice.
余計なアドバイスをして
被験者を追い込むなよ
（リライフ社員）
干渉のし過ぎはよくないな
You can't get emotionally involved.
それではリライフの意味がない
You'll undermine the ReLIFE process.
Right...
Have a good long think about your role here.
（リライフ社員）
もう一度よく考えてみることだ
自分の立場を
Decide who Yoake Ryo
should be to subject no. 001.
（リライフ社員）
被験者001に対して 夜明 了(りょう)は—
どうあるべきなのかを
〜♪
Test Subject 001 -> 002
Calling
Hello?
（夜明）もしもし どうしました？
何か問題でも？
What's the matter? Is there a problem?
ReLIFE Experiment Report
I see.
なるほど もちろんそれは
こちらでも把握していますが
Naturally, we are already aware of that.
でもそれは 僕がどうこうする
問題じゃありません
But that's not a problem I can solve.
The goal of ReLIFE is to give you experience.
リライフは経験を通して
あなた自身が考え 行動し—
To let you grow through
your own thoughts and actions.
成長するためのプログラムです
僕がそんなに干渉したら—
If I get too involved,
実験の意味がなくなってしまいます
it will have no value as an experiment.
焦る必要はありません
頑張ってください
There's no need to rush things.
Hang in there.
Yes.
はい
Well, then, goodbye.
それでは 失礼します
The subject called.
（夜明）被験者より電話があった
Asking for advice is, technically, a change.
助言を求めてきたことは
変化といえば変化だが—
But I can't say for sure if it's a good sign.
それが よい兆候であるとは
言い切ることはできない
I'll maintain my distance and observe...
引き続き距離を保ち
経過を…
Yeah, yeah, I'm about to send the report...
報告書なら
今から送ろうと思って… ん？
Suitability evaluation?
適正調査？
Subject... 002...
被験者… 002
Welcome!
（海崎）いらっしゃいませ
Kaizaki Arata. Twenty-seven.
（夜明）海崎新太 27歳
社交的で面倒見はよいが
現在 定職には就かず—
Sociable and helpful,
but unable to get steady work.
半引きこもり中
Half shut-in.
被験者002の第１候補
Prime candidate for subject no. 002.
He's serious.
真面目だなあ
表情はちょっと暗いけど—
A little gloomy looking, but...
But I guess that's not unusual
late-night convenience store service.
夜のコンビニの接客なら
こんなもんか
Welcome.
（海崎）いらっしゃいませ
Want me to warm that up?
お弁当 温めますか？
Nah, it's my breakfast.
ああ いいです 朝ごはんなんで
（海崎）627円になります
ポイントカードはお持ちですか？
That'll be 627 yen.
Do you have a point card?
（夜明）ああ いいです
Nah, I'm good.
Exact change.
ちょうどいただきます
Thank you!
ありがとうございました
Sir!
お客様！
財布 落とされてませんか？
Have you dropped your wallet?
うわあ ありがとうございます
助かります
Whoa, thank you!
You're a life-saver!
いや 気をつけてお帰りください
Don't mention it.
Please take care.
I thought I put it somewhere
hard for him to spot.
（夜明）
レジから見えにくい位置に—
置いてきたつもり
だったんだけど—
気づくの早かったな
He sure saw it fast.
周囲をよく見ている
行動力もある
Watches his surroundings.
Takes action.
Not bad.
いいんじゃないかな
A completely different type
from subject no. 001.
被験者001とは
まるで違ったタイプ
（小野屋(おのや)）先輩！
（夜明）ん？
Senpai!
（小野屋の荒い息）
（夜明）小野屋 来てたのか
Onoya? You came?
（小野屋）ハァ
What are you doing here?
何やってるんですか？
（夜明）海崎新太の適正調査
Eval on Kaizaki Arata.
何で先輩が？
Why you, Senpai?
I want to be his support!
彼は私が担当したいと
思ってるんです
横取りする気ですか？
Are you trying to snatch him from me?
人聞き悪いな 上の命令だよ
That accusation hurts.
It was orders from above.
後輩の被験者候補も
チェックしておけって
"Check out your junior's candidate."
何だ そうだったんですか
Oh, is that all?
What'd you think of him?
どうです？ 海崎さん
いい人そうでしょ？
Seems like a good guy, huh?
（小野屋）やっぱり
定番の３年生からですかね？
Are we gonna start him in the third year?
（夜明）人付き合いに
問題はなさそうだし—
Looks like he'll have no problems
socially, so that'd work fine.
３年でいいんじゃないのかな
先輩のほうはどうなんです？
被験者001
And how are you doing with subject no. 001?
I'm doing my job.
やってるよ ちゃんと
上から言われたとおりに
Just the way the bosses want me to.
そうじゃなくて—
Not that!
実験が成功しそうかどうかを
聞いたんですけど…
I'm asking if the experiment
will succeed or not...
（夜明）さあ どうだろうね
（小野屋）えー？
Well, who knows?
We're talking about a human being here.
You never know what'll happen.
（夜明）人間相手なんだから—
何が起こるか
分からないってことだよ
どうすれば結果につながるのか
どこまでやっていいのか
What can you do to get results?
How far can you push things?
It's hard to find the right distance.
距離感が難しいんだ
ReLIFE Experiment Report
Handler: Yoake Ryo
Subject:
There was so much potential.
How could this happen?
（リライフ社員）かなり見込みが
あるはずだったのに—
どうなってるんだ？
Our branch's first subject,
and this is the result?
我が支部 第１号の被験者が
こんな結果だなんて
I'm ashamed to show my face
around the other branches.
恥ずかしくて ほかの支部に
顔向けできないだろう
ReLIFE Experiment Reports
１年経って何の変化もないなんて
A whole year without any change...
夜明のサポートが
足りなかったんじゃないのか？
Did you not do enough
to support the subject?
ReLIFE Experiment Report
Handler: Yoake Ryo
Subject:
先輩…
Senpai...
I've observed you for a year
and reported on it.
（夜明）あなたのこの１年を観察し
報告してきましたが—
就職先としてご紹介できる企業は
ないということになりそうです
But it seems like we'll be unable
to set you up with any work.
I apologize.
申し訳ありません
My support wasn't good enough.
僕のサポートが
至らなかったばかりに
What should I have done?
どうすれば よかったんだろうね
They told me I was too involved.
干渉しすぎだと
言われて—
So I stepped back.
距離をとったら
サポートが足りないって言われて
Then they told me I didn't do enough.
さっき—
A few minutes ago,
被験者002が海崎新太さんに
決定したって連絡がありました
we received word that they've picked
Kaizaki Arata-san as subject no. 002.
And his support...
担当は—
Change of support for the start of
the Kanto Branch's subject no. 002 experiment.
Support: Yoake Ryo
夜明 了
...was Yoake Ryo.
It was you.
（小野屋）先輩です
（夜明）あっ
They said to start prepping at once.
（小野屋）すぐ準備を始めろって
You don't have time to mope!
落ち込んでる暇 ないですよ！
（夜明）被験者002 海崎新太
Subject no. 002, Kaizaki Arata.
あはは
（夜明）小野屋 恨んでるだろうな
Onoya must be pissed at me.
あれだけ気に入ってた被験者を—
She really wanted to support
this test subject,
and I wound up snatching him anyway.
結局
横取りする形になっちゃったし
でも これも仕事だ
割り切るしかない
But it's my job.
Gotta deal with it.
Whoa, wai—
（海崎）ああっ
ちょ ちょっと待…
俺の人生 どうして
こうなっちゃったんだろう
How did my life turn out like this?
Good evening.
こんばんは はじめまして
Nice to meet you, Kaizaki Arata-san.
海崎新太さん
I'm Yoake Ryo,
from the ReLIFE Laboratory.
わたくし
リライフ研究所の—
夜明 了という者です
１年間 高校生になって—
Will you become a student for a year and
see this as a chance to change your life?
今の人生を変えられる
チャンスだと思うか
おじけづいて このままずるずる
ニート生活を続けていくか
Or will you get cold feet, back out,
and keep living as a NEET?
The choice is yours, Kaizaki-san.
どちらを選ぶかは
海崎さん次第です
実際 もう
つらかったでしょう
It was rough on you, right?
Pretending you had a real job
in front of your friends.
会社員のフリをして
お友達と 話合わせるの
引き受けていただけるなら—
If you're ready to accept,
please sign the contract.
契約書にサインを
お願いしたいのですが
よいリライフにしましょう
Here's to a good ReLIFE.
This man...
（夜明）この人は 果たして—
I wonder...
What kind of ReLIFE will he show me?
どんなリライフを
見せてくれるんだろう
（小野屋）はーい
Coming!
先輩をこき使うとは
いい根性だね 小野屋
You've got a lot of nerve making
your senpai work like this, Onoya.
あはは すみませーん
Sorry!
研究所にいるっていうから—
You were at the lab and coming here anyway,
こっちのほう来るついでに
持ってきてもらおうと思って
so I figured you could bring it
while you were at it.
ついでっていう重さと
距離じゃないんだけど
It was too heavy and too far
to bring "while I was at it."
まあ どうぞどうぞ
お礼にコーヒーぐらい出しますよ
Well, come on in.
I'll make some coffee as a thank you.
Support Division
Onoya An
Aoba High
Uniform, Textbooks
（小野屋）うわあー セーラーだ
懐かしいなあ
A sailor suit!
This takes me back!
あたしも高校の時
セーラーだったんですよ
My actual high school
also had sailor uniforms.
いやあ この歳になって
また着ることになろうとは
Never thought I'd wear one again at my age.
I know, right,
ほんとにねえ
ババアが
old bag.
If I'm an old bag,
that makes you a geezer.
あたしがババアなら
先輩もジジイですからね
ほんと 楽しみです
I'm really looking forward to this!
４月から まさか
先輩と同じ高校になって—
I never imagined that starting April,
I'd be in the same school
同級生って！ ウフッ うける〜
and same class as you!
That's hilarious!
（小野屋）海崎さんはどうでした？
（夜明）え？
How was Kaizaki-san?
Huh?
被験者002の海崎新太さんですよ
Subject no. 002, Kaizaki Arata-san!
You met with him today, right?
今日 会ってきたんじゃ
ないですか？
He signed the contract.
契約は問題なく成立したよ
うまくやって
いけそうですか？
Think you'll work well with him?
うまくやっていくのが
サポート課の仕事だよ
That's our job as support.
さすが先輩
Damn right, Senpai!
Man, you really get on my nerves.
なんかムカつく
えー？ どうしてですか？
Huh? Why?
ま 海崎さんなら大丈夫ですよ
Well, you don't need to worry
about Kaizaki-san.
人柄が文句なしなのは
調査済みですもんね
We already made sure
his personality wouldn't be a problem.
Yeah.
（夜明）そうだね
でも—
But...
I think people like that
have problems that run deep.
そういう人ほど—
内に抱える問題の根は
深いんじゃないのかな
大切に思う人を失うきっかけが—
The trauma of thinking you
might have been the reason
自分にあったかもしれない
というトラウマは—
that you lost someone you cared about
簡単に消えるもんじゃないよ
doesn't go away easily.
"Was there more I could have done?"
もっとやれることが
あったんじゃないか
"Perhaps I shouldn't have
done anything at all?"
逆に何もしないほうがよかったのか
Now that he has no way
of knowing for sure,
もうそれを
確かめることができない今—
Kaizaki-san has lost confidence
in his social skills.
海崎さんは すべての人間関係に
自信をなくしてる
本来 人のために
あんな風に動ける人がだよ？
Normally, he'd go way out
on a limb for someone, but...
But isn't that what
makes him perfect for ReLIFE?
だからこその
リライフなんじゃないですか？
海崎さんに自信を
取り戻してもらうためのリライフ
ReLIFE will help Kaizaki-san
get his confidence back.
It'll be fine.
大丈夫ですよ
海崎さんと先輩なら
You guys can do it together.
だといいけど
I sure hope so.
Onoya, you're really flattering me today.
小野屋 今日はずいぶん
持ち上げてくれるんだね
Huh? Am I?
え？ そうですか？
It's creepy.
（夜明）気持ち悪い
（小野屋）何ですか それ！
What? I'm just cheering you on!
これでも応援してるんですよ
ふっ やっぱり気持ち悪い
See? Creepy.
You're so mean!
（小野屋）ひどーい
Hello, Kaizaki-san!
どうも海崎さん
こんな夜遅くにどうしたんですか？
What do you need this late?
（海崎）悪い
ちょっと相談したいことがあって
Sorry...
I need to talk to you about something.
元に戻る薬が欲しい？
Medicine to turn you back...?
知り合いとかに１年は会えないって
連絡してたんだけど—
I let everyone know I wouldn't
see 'em for a year, but...
バイト先 さすがに電話１本で
急には辞められねえだろ
But I can't just call in to quit my job.
Just cut them loose.
もうブッチすれば
いいじゃないですか
はあ？ ありえねえだろ！
どんな神経してんだよ
I could never...!
What's wrong with you?
ふふふっ 分かりました
Okay, got it.
薬は申請しておきますよ
I'll request the medicine.
It'll be a day or two, though.
お渡しは明日以降になっちゃうと
思いますけど
（海崎）ああ よろしく
Okay, that's fine.
では
Goodbye, then.
Research and Development
お疲れさまでーす
Hello!
天ヶ瀬(あまがせ)さん 薬剤申請お願いします
Amagase-san, I have a medicine request.
（天ヶ瀬）おっ 最近よく来るな
You're here a lot lately.
お疲れ 夜明
Doing all right, Yoake?
One present and one past
for subject no. 002.
（夜明）被験者002の
現形と過去形 １個ずつ と
Medicine Request
And one of each for you?
（天ヶ瀬）夜明のも追加か？
被験者に薬を渡すために会うので
いったん元の姿に戻ります
I'll meet the subject
to hand over the medicine,
so I'd like to look my age.
何でそんな手間を
そのまま行きゃいいだろう
Why bother?
Just go as you are.
No, no!
僕のこの姿をさらすのは
登校初日までとっておいて—
I don't want him to see me like this
until I surprise him
on the first day of school!
ああっと驚かせたいじゃないですか
どんな顔するんだろうって
ゾクゾクします
I can't wait to see the look on his face!
Well, that's the official reason.
（夜明）
ってのは まあ建て前で
サポート役がばっちり同じクラスに
いるって事前に分かっちゃ—
I just think if he knows the support
will be in class with him,
少なからず被験者の気が
緩んでしまうと思うので
he won't stress about it enough.
へえ ちゃんと考えてんだな
You've thought it through.
それがサポート課ですから
That is my job.
じゃ 明日取りに来ますんで
よろしくお願いします
I'll drop by tomorrow to pick them up.
Thank you!
Sure thing.
ハァ
お疲れさまでした
You look wiped.
ああ 緊張した
Yeah... that was stressful.
緊張？
Stressful?
It was just a part-time job.
そりゃ
ただのバイトだったけど—
But the boss was nice.
Helped me out a lot.
店長いい人だし
いろいろ世話になったからな
なんか 申し訳なくて
I feel guilty quitting.
Thanks for going along with this.
わがまま聞いてくれてありがとな
Now I can go back to school
without any regrets.
これで心おきなく高校生をやれる
えっ もうここで
飲んじゃうんですか？
You're just gonna take it here?
Takes a while for it to kick in, right?
薬が効くのに 時間かかるんだろ？
やる気まんまんですね
You're gung-ho about this.
し… 仕方ねえだろ
バイトもう辞めちゃったし
I-I'd better be!
I even quit my job.
もう これしかやることねえんだし
I don't have any other options.
俺は何事もなく—
I'm just gonna hunker down
and let the year go by.
さらっと１年が過ぎてくれりゃあ
それでいいんだよ
That's all.
やる気とかじゃねえよ
Not exactly gung-ho.
Got it.
はい
あ… 渡した資料に
書かれてますけど—
It's in the documents I gave you,
その薬 飲んだ直後に—
but you'll get really sleepy shortly
after taking that, so be careful.
猛烈な眠気がくるので
気をつけてくださいね
（海崎）えっ
（夜明）車の運転などは—
I'd advise you not to drive anywhere.
くれぐれも控えて
持ってねえよ 車なんか
I don't have a car!
But, uh...
あっ つうか
この後 まだ予定があんのに
I have plans after this...
まったく無計画な人ですねえ
You're so thoughtless.
ちゃんと説明しなかったほうに
問題はねえのかよ
Isn't it your fault for not
explaining it to me properly?!
（夜明）ははははっ
それもそうですね
Fair enough!
（海崎）“そうですね”って！
Fair enough?!
（夜明）
資料は ちゃんと読んでください
You should really read the documents.
（海崎）あっ 夜明さん
（夜明）えっ？
（夜明）
海崎新太においては 毎回—
But each time Kaizaki Arata
demonstrates remorse,
反省と改善の態度も見られ—
and attempts to improve...
その前向きな姿勢は—
...and that forward-thinking
nature is infectious.
確実に周囲の人間をも
巻き込んで—
He's starting to change things around him.
環境自体に
変化をもたらし始めている
それが
海崎新太のリライフにおいて—
What effect will that have
on Kaizaki Arata's ReLIFE?
どう作用するのか
It makes me want to keep watching
今後も 彼らと共に
高校生活を送りながら—
and living a student's life with them.
観察を続けていきたいと思う
〜♪
NEXT EPISODE
Yoake-san, what do you usually do?
（海崎）
夜明さんはさ 普段何してんの？
（夜明）何とは？
What do you mean?
（海崎）いや
俺のサポート以外の時間は—
I mean, what do you do when
you're not supporting me?
どうしてんのかなあと
（夜明）もちろん—
I keep thinking about you, of course!
ずっと海崎さんのことばかり
考えてますよ
Rift
（海崎）え！
（夜明）って言ってほしいですか？
Huh?
Is that what you want me to say?
（海崎）ほしくねえよ！
Hell, no!